what is going on guys welcome back in
this video today we're going to learn
how to turn postgress into a vector
database in order for example to store
embeddings from large language models so
let's get right into
[Music]
ited all right so we're going to learn
how to turn postgress into a vector
database in this video today and we're
going to do that by using PG Vector
which is an open source extension for
postgress and why would we want do that
for example to store embeddings created
by large language models in order to
build a recommender system that would be
one use case you have a bunch of
different movies or books or items in a
store and what we do is we feed the
information in textual form as a prompt
so to say to a large language model and
the large language model returns a
high-dimensional vector and this Vector
uh is created in an intelligent way so
that the different vectors if they are
similar if the items that are um
embedded so to say are similar they end
up quite close to one another in the
vector space whereas if they are very
different they end up uh further apart
in the vector space that's the basic
idea of creating embeddings using large
language models and you don't need to
use a Pure Vector database like phas for
example in order to do that you can do
that with postgress if you install the
PG Vector extension which is what we're
going to do in this video today so the
goal is to get some items uh create some
embeddings using a large language model
I'm going to use the open AI API so GPT
you can also go with an o llama llama 2
model depending on if you want to run
this locally or uh using some API it
doesn't really matter the only thing
that you need to consider is the
dimensionality so the different llms
will return vectors of a different size
of a different dimension so this is
something that you have to uh take into
account but besides that it doesn't
really matter how you do it you just
have um the embeddings and we're going
to use PG Vector to store the embeddings
and to perform a similarity search for
for example a recommender system um all
right now it's not going to be part of
this video to set up postgress so I
assume you either have postgress
installed already or you know how to do
it so I'm not going to go through uh
installing postgress server and setting
up a user and uh granting the
permissions and so on I assume you
already have this running or you don't
want to follow along or you know how to
do it yourself I'm not going to go
through the steps here um but if you
have postp installed already what you
need to do is you need to install PG
Vector on your system so you want to go
to the get up repository you will find a
link to it in the description down below
and you want to go um and clone this
repository uh so either get clone or
download the zip file and extract it and
then depending on your operating system
you just run a simple command on Windows
you run this call command and on Linux
and Mac you go into the into the
repository you run make and you run make
install in my case as it already says
here I needed to run pseudo make install
so it needed some elevated
permissions um and then you basically
have PG Vector on your system now this
doesn't mean that you already have it in
your database so you need to do that uh
separately but once you have this
installed what you want to do is you
want to open up a terminal and create a
new database or use an existing one if
you want to so in my case here this is
going to be um let's call this
create uh Vector DB or vector tutorial
DB whatever I just create a new not
create sorry create DB is the command uh
create DB Vector tutorial DB this is
going to create a new postgress database
and what I want to do now is I want to
connect to it now of course this uh
means you have to have the PG HBA config
file set up properly so that you can log
in and and all that but again this is
not a video on postgress just connect to
the database the way you do uh usually
so in this case I'm going to go with
psql uh host is Local Host and then
username is postgress and DB name is uh
vector tutorial
DB
um and then it's going to ask for a
password a password in my case postgress
and now I'm in the database here so I
can look at this I don't have any tables
here and what I want to do now is I want
to create the extension so I want to
actually um enable the vector extension
so what I do is I say create extension
if not
exists Vector like this so This command
here create extension if not exist let
me just make this a little bit larger
for you guys um if I run this now this
creates the extension vector and now my
database supports vectors and now I can
create a table that can store items
um that that that can store items with
vectors or that can store vectors in the
in the table so I'm going to say now
create table items for example and now I
can Define the usual Fields I can say I
want to have an ID which is a
Serial so an autoincrement primary
key I want to have a name uh which is
going to be the text or I can say maybe
let's call this content text and then I
want to have the embedding so the
embedding is going to be a vector this
is now we need the Plugin or the
extension and this Vector has a
dimensionality now if we use llama 2 I
think we get
4,096 as the dimension if we use open AI
GPT we get 1 ,
536 so depending on the language model
that you use make sure you know what the
embedding dimensions are uh or the size
of the vectors that are the embeddings
are and then create the table with this
dimensionality so run this create table
we now have the table now I can quit I
can exit and this database now can store
um the vectors of the
size all right so what I want to do now
next in Python is I want to connect to
this database create some embeddings and
uh store them in the
database so what I'm going to do for
this video here is I'm going to use some
very basic data just to Showcase um the
concept here I think you already know or
a lot of you guys already know how this
works I just created some basic texts
that have some similarity I just created
them in a way that uh shows that these
similari is not determined by specific
words in terms of the words are similar
but also on uh in terms of the meaning
so I'm going to Showcase uh showcase
this here but first of all we want to
open up a terminal and install the
following packages so pip 3 install want
to install psycho pg2 which is for
postgress uh we want to install numpy
and we want to install Lang chain so
these are the three packages that we
need in this video today and then we're
going to start by saying import psychop
pg2 import numpy asnp and from lank
chain embeddings import open a
embeddings now this is just because I'm
using the open AI embeddings if you're
using different embeddings you want to
use a different uh class here and now
I'm going to copy paste here my prepared
uh text you can use whatever you want
here you can craft your own stuff you
can load a data set in my case here what
I'm doing is I have a couple of uh
configurations of computers so I have a
desktop PC a laptop uh with different
operating systems Manjaro Windows Fedora
a buntu with different um GPU brands
with different CPU brands with different
Ram sizes and with different uh SSD
sizes so very simple and I want to find
now to a given uh text
the uh the most similar model that I
have already now one more UT here which
I forgot is the OS import this is core
python um and what we're going to do
here now is we're going to load the API
key that is needed in my case here I
have it stored in a text file and we're
going to load the API key from this text
file here so um what you need to do for
this of course is you need to go to the
open AI platform you need to go to
settings and create an API key it's
basically something that starts with SK
Dash and then some uh long string and
what I'm going to do here now is I'm
going to say API or actually I need to
load this as an environment variable so
os. Environ and then in the square
brackets here I'm going to say uh open
aior API key this is important because
this environment varable will be used by
Lang chain to authenticate uh with the
open AI API to be able to use GPT so
we're going to set this to and then um
open API key in reading mode read so
this is going to load my API key into
the environment variable and now I can
create the embeddings using lank chain
so I can say embeddings is equal to open
AI embeddings
and then I can say embedding embeddings
list is going to be equal to an empty
list and then for text in
texts I'm going to say embedding
list append and then we want to embed
the actual text so embeddings which is
the open AI embeddings object here embed
query text and then we have a list of
embeddings created by the open AI uh
model the embedding model now I'm not
sure actually which one is used by
default it depends probably on the
version of your package uh but it's
going to use some decent embedding model
and uh we can also see here so I can
look at embedding list and you can see I
have these vectors and I can also look
at the first element for example and I
think is this a list or is this an numpy
array so if it's a list we should be
able to get the or actually also it's a
numpy array there you go the length of
this is 1,536
which is exactly the dimensionality of
the vector that we uh created in a
database or the field that we created in
a database and now what we're going to
do is we're going to store D embeddings
in our postgress uh database so I'm
going to say here now the connection is
going to be equal to psychop pg2 connect
and we're going to use the following
connection string or connection
parameters here DB name is going to be
equal to what did I call this actually
did I call this Vector tutorial EB I
think so
user is going to be equal to postgress
and password is also going to be equal
to postgress in this
case uh and then I'm going to create a
cursor which is going to be a
connection.
cursor and now I'm going to go through
the embeddings list and I'm going to
insert the items um I'm going to insert
the items into the postgress database so
for I
in uh range length embedding list
I'm going to say the embedding that I
want to embed or that I want to insert
into a database is embeddings list uh I
and then the
corresponding content is going to be
equal to the text at disp position so
the reason I also want to insert the
text into database is because I want to
get of course the most similar uh result
but I also want to be able to map it
back to the actual content so if some if
the database tells me that given a
certain string the most similar computer
setup is or configuration is five I
don't know what this is unless I also
have the text in there so content is
equal to text I and then cursor execute
the following statement quite simple
we're just going to say insert
into uh what did I call it items values
or actually we need to say name
embedding actually I'm still using name
because in my prepared code I'm using
name uh content embeddings or embedding
um values and then we have here
um a prepared statement so two
placeholders and then we're going to say
here content and
embedding as a
tupo there you go so this is just to
prevent uh SQL injections and then we
say connection commit and then we say
cursor
close and then we say connection close
so this inserts the items into the
database now I'm not sure do I have my
terminal still open no this is just my
jupyter notebook um I could actually
connect to the database and see if we
can already see this stuff in there so P
SQL host Local
Host user name is postgress DB
name Vector tutorial
DB and then select everything from
items um did it work or not not
sure let me just double check if I did
everything correctly insert into
items um I think it should have worked
so let's see if the code Works maybe
just the display um didn't do this
properly or it wasn't display properly
but what we're going to do now is we're
going to get a new text or a new yeah
actually a new text and I'm going to say
that this is I'm going to copy paste
this again here from my prepared code um
this is the following system and I'm
going to say I'm going to explain here
why I chose this system you can see that
this is a desktop PC with the Arch Linux
operating system now we don't have an
Arch Linux operating system here we have
mararo though which I would consider to
be the most similar because um yeah of
course mararo is also Arch based and um
because of that we're going to say Now
new
embedding is equal to
embeddings do query new
text and oh sorry embed query new text
um and then we're going to say now I
want to find the most
similar uh Vector in the database how do
we do that well we do first of all um a
connection again so I'm going to just
copy paste
this we connect to the database again
and then we run the following command so
cursor uh
execute and we're going to run this as a
multi-line command here as a multi-line
string we're going to say select ID and
content uh from
items
order by and now here we're going to use
this operator provided by PG Vector we
have the
embedding and then we use uh these
double arrows here so basically uh these
angle brackets with a hyphen in between
uh and we're going to say now here
percent s and then uh colon colon vector
and we're going to say limit five for
example to get the top five results and
this here now is going to be our new
embedding so the basic idea is we want
to select the ID um or the IDS and the
contents uh from the items table where
the embedding of this particular object
in the table is the most similar to the
vector that we pass and we specify that
this is a vector by using colon colon
vector and um this here is basically a
similarity search now what's the problem
here oh this is a tuple so we need to
pass a comma um and then we can get the
results by saying results is equal to
cursor fetch
all for Row in results we can print the
row and
this did not work as expected so let me
just double check what I did wrong here
okay so I figured out what the problem
is uh it shouldn't be text ey obviously
but texts I plural because we don't want
to have the I character of the text that
was processed here uh in the last
iteration we want to have the I element
of this text list so we need to do it
like this uh then we need to run all
this again the problem is of course that
this is going to still give us the old
um Elements which is why we need to
actually truncate the table I think for
this though we need to say Connection
close
first um and then we're going to say
truncate table
items and now we should have nothing in
this table so I'm going to uh run
actually all of this here again there
you go and we see uh that mararo is the
most similar uh or this computer here
with Manjaro is the most similar to our
computer even though the auntu and the
Windows system have the ex same uh exact
same um Ram size and GPU brand and CPU
brand and uh hard disk or SSD size uh or
capacity here but of course Manjaro is
the most similar because it's an arch
based distro we have a buntu which is a
Linux based distro and then we have
Windows which is not Linux at all and uh
actually Linux Min should probably be
more similar but this is just one
example what we can also do here I have
a second example prepared is is uh where
I want to showcase how this works if I
delete this and I replace it by these
texts here my computer was made by Apple
my favorite fruit is Apple so it's the
same word but a different meaning my
atems Apple hurts my knee seems a today
my laptop is running Arch Linux my
breakfast usually includes berries now
in this case here the reason I chose
these uh strings is because of course
the Apple here should be more similar to
Arch Linux or to laptop whereas um this
apple here should be more similar to
berri's and the atams Apple should be
more similar to a knee so even though
the word Apple occurs three times here
it has a different meaning a different
context and this should probably be
picked up I hope it's uh it's picked up
by the uh large language model so we're
going to do the same thing here let me
just truncate the table briefly again um
do we have a connection open I hope not
so let me just truncate the table again
and we're going to input all of these
into the database and now the new text
is going to be a different one the new
text is going to be uh let's play around
with my
desktops always run
Windows and if I run this now you can
see that my computer was made by Apple
my laptop is running Arch Linux this is
recognized as the most similar um
whereas if I do something like my dinner
would benefit from adding apples to
it then you can see that um these two
are the most similar so even though the
term apples uh occurs here this is the
most similar and this is the most
similar the second most similar and the
other uh apples are less similar than
berries because the Apple word has a
different meaning so you can see that
the embeddings are done in an
intelligent way but this is how we can
use postgress as a vector database uh to
perform similarity search on embeddings
so that's it for today's video I hope
you enjoyed it and hope you learned
something if so let me know by hitting a
like button and leaving a comment in the
comment section down below and of course
don't forget to subscribe to this
Channel and hit the notification Bell to
not miss a single future video for free
other than that thank you much for
watching see you in the next video and
bye